great wonderful
I am so nice to have this opportunity to
do this interview with you we met um I
can't remember was it in 2009 that you
came oh I don't know I can't remember
I'm too old to remember those things but
it was a horn yeah remember that first
you came to Finland and then I also
always remember when I went to see is we
went to the National History Museum
which I loved and still have the t-shirt
great yeah no I remember that because I
pulled out into the traffic going the
wrong way I think I scared your pants
off you the policeman pulled up but you
see brother nervous I said no no it's
cool sure enough he got out held up the
traffic so we could turn around and I
would love to because for so long um
this word I did more and more people are
using the word consciousness every day
now and saying that ultimately the shift
we now need to make is so deep in terms
of redesigning as David all would call
it redesigning the human presence on
earth and within the lifetime of the
generations life today
and that's a tall order and and most of
them are in intelligent perspectives
that I read on this all agreed that
ultimately we need a shift in
consciousness before we have a chance of
redesigning because it's ultimately in
the way we see the world the way we see
ourselves and the way we understand the
relationship between consciousness and
matter it's um
so much of the problems that we've
created actually rooted and it's one of
those words that lots of people use but
you wrote a wonderful
called consciousness explained better
short little book it was a take on
Daniel Dennett Daniel did is explained
or some people say should have been
consciousness explained away because you
know he's such a reductionist in fact
ISA physicalist I would say he's proud
of it so yeah what I one of the best
statements about consciousness that I've
read is from an article that you call
authored with Ken Wilber in 2010 and I'm
just gonna read this statement here and
it's consciousness is so much more than
an evolutionary accident or an
epiphenomenon of biochemical processes
in our heads consciousness is in fact
fundamentally woven into the universe
itself what we are saying is that what
we are saying is that to some degree of
subjectivity is indeed present in all
the way all the way up and all the way
down in the evolutionary ladder from the
tiniest quarks to the biggest brains
this consciousness can be loosely
described as a perspective making and
perspective-taking system that creates
collects organizes deeper wider and more
sophisticated sophisticated points of
view as it develops
so it's an evolutionary developmental
view that starts with then basically any
perspective taking is an act of bringing
forth a world and we bring the world
together in that jewel of Indra from all
those perspectives whether there he is
taking or whether it's a sequoia tree
taking perspective of its environment am
i understanding that correctly or could
you elaborate on that by the way I love
that I don't know where it's at maybe
you could send it to me I I don't really
remember where it's at but or writing it
but sounds right
I find this I think it wasn't one of Ken
Wilbur's websites an article no but it's
a great quote well it brings up several
points that we could talk about quite a
bit sort of prefigures a what today
we're seeing more and more philosophers
and scientists shifting to a kind of pan
psychist view and psychism that is
consciousness is somehow fundamental to
the to the world and to the universe
Christian De Quincey wrote a wonderful
book about this years ago that urban
Laughlin was so impressed whether he had
a whole conference based on it I think
it's called radical knowing but if you
go to Christian De Quincey he's sort of
an independent scholar on the west coast
he has his own website and he teaches
courses but he's written several books
but this was his first one and which he
makes a good case for the idea that
consciousness is interwoven I shouldn't
say it it's a feature of the universe
and so it's not exactly panned psychism
but pretty close to it and he makes a
good good case for that the idea of
pants ideas and the idea of that
consciousness permeates everything in
some sense or other see I'm going to go
to the big meeting at Tucson in a month
or two that this is the biggest
conference conference in the world and
it meets in Tucson every other year
which is its home base but the next year
it will be in Italy for example last
year was in Switzerland so it's the
different places but I have been coming
since the beginning 26 or 27 years
they've been
and it's directed by Stuart Hameroff
who's probably the most prominent
scientists in the world who argues for
quantum events in the brain it's a root
of consciousness and and he works at the
University of Tucson or Arizona there
he's a geologist by trade but he's one
of these very bright guys I think his
first book years ago was on quantum
computing and he got together with David
Chalmers it was at the time 20 years ago
twenty seven years ago a young
philosopher and the two of them began to
organize these conferences well Chalmers
first argued that consciousness is
information and yes if its earliest
books a very good book on consciousness
although he made price argue for this
theory of consciousness is information I
wish could be right or could be wrong
but the point is that he and the last
year for unities become apparent
psychist and so when people of his
recognition and caliber in the academy
become pants I mean this is a guy that
hangs out with Daniel Dennett for
example it and with the elite what I
would call northeastern school of
philosophers who are very distant very
arrogant in their own way and very elite
and here he is somehow he's gotten in
with him I'm not sure exactly how but
he's done it and he's become a pant
sizes so he's an example of the way the
wind is blowing if I can put it that way
because ken Wilber and I have always
been pants itis in some sense or we've
always felt that consciousness is shared
by virtually all highly organized living
organisms and we're friendly to the idea
that maybe it goes down deeper than that
maybe molecules are limited on ik
particles have some
kind of preconscious if not conscious
element dude it's really hard to
describe but what I find interesting is
that like yet yesterday I talked to
Fritjof Capra and and we were spending
it spent quite some time talking about
the Santiago theory of cognition and we
also talked about the question what is
life and for me it seems like the
question what is life and what is
consciousness I actually very closely
linked and to some extent Madonna and
Marilla very much influenced by Gregory
Bateson I believe em port 4 with this
theory that to some extent explains both
what is life and what is consciousness
in a similar way as that quote I just
read by you and Ken M because it is
about that it's the act of distinction
the act of perspective taking that there
actually defines self and world the
individual and the soul felt environment
but they're actually Einstein called
this an illusion of conscious
consciousness that in the act of taking
the perspective we begin to believe that
there is an other but that others eye is
only a larger dimension of yourself
becoming aware of itself and I know this
sounds like it's very difficult to put
these things in language but I'm i've
been grappling with this for years
does that resonate with you at all well
I'm a big enthusiast Pharrell is mighty
Rama's concept of auto poiesis which i
think is you know really basic to the
organization of life self building self
creating you know without going into in
detail I'm sure you're very familiar
with it and a lot of people hear this
this tape will be familiar with it but
it's simply the idea that the organism
the processes of the organism say a
single
or a living animal or any living and
creature that in some the output of the
whole process is the organism itself for
the cell itself that entire complex
metabolism of a living cell is in the
business of producing that living cell
in the next moment I think that's a very
basic and important idea I have to say
that no criticism intended but I was
never impressed with the notion of
inaction much and I I could say more but
I don't know whether you want me to talk
more about it well people get really
excited about inaction and I don't see
anything new in it frankly that Jerome
Bruner wrote about the importance of
inaction and cognitive systems and
learning back in the 60s John Dewey
wrote about it in the 19th century the
notion of bringing forth our worlds then
we are well now wait a minute now that's
bringing forth a world that's why I
would like you to just define what you
mean by inaction so people understand
well it's just that the organism is in a
very active relationship with the
environment or with other organisms and
so there's this action going back and
forth and so you know as I said in John
Dewey's and Jerome Bruner it's in Piaget
it's got a new name but I'm sorry I wish
I could say I was excited about it but
I'm just not I think the the idea of
bringing forth the world is an
interesting turn of phrase but I don't
think there's any news in it basically
went for a new Varela by the way but not
real real well he was part of urban
lassos
crippled an urban started writing about
weird and wonderful things like life
continuing after death he got off the
boat he was not hidden one part of that
so but I did see him in a number of
meetings so where was I with this I
think it's a different way I mean okay
open your eyes and look around the room
now you've created a world now what kind
of the world in your own experience and
you can interact with it I don't see
anything more profound in it than that
but you have to remember that real is
not your honest concept of an organism
it's a very close or the thing is this
metaphor at length of a submarine it's
like a submarine it's got this periscope
and it's like yeah it's a little
periscope I used to argue all the time
with my friend Soren Breyer who's a
eminent some at assist semiotic sister
actually biosemiotics is he ran the
journal for years and he would always
take their side I would say well I don't
see I don't agree with this I don't
think an organism is a closed system and
someone would say what really means
closed in terms of processes and so we
would go back and forth but the s
important part or the way the thing came
down for me is that an organism is a
closed system that they use the mint or
the submarine with the periscope and
then they could look out this periscope
at a very limited world and then it
could connect with other organisms in
with the environment but it was a very
limited connection and just I never
could rush inside now maybe I'm not
smart enough I know a lot of smart
people think about this but I think the
organism is open in all kinds of ways
ecologically opened it organically open
and so on so I never I never got on
board with that I mean I personally and
this
this is more of a intuitive
understanding based on some study but I
sense that we might actually have it
wrong
focusing too much on the individual
organism or even the individual species
and we um if we understood life as a
planetary process that is through this
act of perspective taking basically
becoming conscious of itself more and
therefore getting better feedback on how
to organize the complexity that it
creates in order to be better at
creating conditions conducive to life if
you wanna can frame it under Janine
Benyus is nice biomimicry so if that's
what life does it creates conditions
conducive to life and for me this on the
one hand the the notion that it doesn't
really make sense that there's a dead
matter universe out there and then at
some level of complexity keishon of dead
bits organizing each other life pops up
life bits organizing some of these life
forms have a bit of consciousness I
think it actually makes me logically
more sense to assume that the whole
thing is to some degree a life and the
whole shouldn't even say things should
say being the whole being of the
universe is to some degree a life and to
some degree conscious but as it
complexified into more and more complex
ways of taking perspective it can
capture more of a perspective as you as
you say in this this sends you like I
love this bit of yeah
spective making perspective-taking
system that creates collects organizes
deeper wider and more sophisticated
point of views as it develops and and
for me if we got to a point where which
I think we've been in in in some of the
wisdom traditions I understand the dual
net of Indra in in the Vedanta as an
expression of exactly that concept that
the whole perceives itself through the
parts but the path the whole so comes
forth through the participation of the
parts in Indonesian in report of
authentic wholeness kind of way and so
for me that the big shift is to stop
because we now everybody talks about
fighting climate change so humanity
survives and if we identify more deeply
with life as a planetary process then
our concern would be life continuing and
our actions in it I like humble
Gardeners contributing what basically
doing what life needs to do which is
creating conditions conducive to life
and and the to make that maturity jump
that we now need to do as a species we
need to reify with that wider process um
just as like Goethe said um 200 years
ago 250 years ago who doesn't see nature
everywhere sees her know we're in the
right light again somewhat unlike is
well worldview because when he speaks of
nature he also speaks of the process of
awareness necessarily fair psychist it's
just the kind of seeing universes of
living whole yeah he reminds me of Walt
Whitman was not a philosopher but he saw
life everywhere and in everything and
was really a mystic in a lot of ways but
yeah I like what you're saying there
were two
things when I wanted to remember
dimension urban Laszlo's recent book the
Intelligent universe or something like
that this was the city publicist was
ending last year - they said he writes
books every weekend I think and he can't
hardly keep up with him he's 10 years
older than me I don't know how yes and I
hope I'm half as smart as he is but he
makes an amazingly intelligent and
well-thought-out argument that the
cosmos as a whole is it is a kind of
living process living organism really
with checks and balances and growth
processes and autopilot processes at
every level and this is an amazing
drawing together of ideas that are out
there have been out there but to think
of the the whole universe as like a
single organism in its levels of
organization and structure and
communication within itself it's just so
wonderful and he convinced me I think
it's one of the most important things he
ever did I think it's one of the most
important books it's ever been written
even though it's just some little book
because it gives you a vision of the
cosmos is a unified process and that
process is growing I'm not in any
trivial sense but it's evolving its
evolving at many levels all the time and
it's and it's it's a dynamic
evolutionary perspective rather than a
dead mechanical universe that we've had
for so long and that led us astray in in
how I mean this is what I mean when
we're talking about bringing forth a
word I love Henry bought Earth's motion
of organizing ideas with rule and that's
why I finally that's where we're the
shift to some extent needs to happen is
we need new organizing ideas
allow us to for example think of the
universe as a living organism and and
garden living yeah and this brings back
another point I want to say before I
forget because I'm getting old and I
forget what I want to talk about
halftime act I mean if just forgotten it
just to prove you where are worried a
minute ago okay I remember you said
we're fighting climate change thought
about Friday you know that especially I
don't know about your panamerican this
is that a real problem and everything we
don't like we're gonna fight we fight
diseases and fight old age gonna have a
battle against poverty and a fight
poverty you know if it's such a poor way
to go about solving a problem exactly
so you know we're not gonna fight the
environment what we got to do is get on
board and do what we can do to
facilitate a natural process that's just
another way of saying hey I quoted these
people not by agreeing with them because
I think that that's exactly the wrong
organizing ideas yet and other it's it
also it starts from a problem rather
than the potential and I think that if
we really go looking with consciousness
then what we what we need to start from
is working from potential flow from the
the potential of us waking up to our
core identity with this larger evolving
process whether we keep it for a while I
think we'd already have a massive
achievement if people understood their
unity with Gaia as a living planet at
the planetary scale but I think that
what you just I haven't read Evans
latest book but the notion of speaking
of the entire universe as an evolving
organism makes complete sense to me
because it other people I have a at
least a pre-publication copy of it so I
don't just shout you're right well let
me come in
on this a little bit it's a person
that's been as you know and very much
involved in the consciousness field the
consciousness
area and I often hear that you know we
and this is what urban is all about we
need to change our consciousness our
knits he writes about it all the time
but it's I think it's I hate to say it's
not that simple but it's not that simple
because you know I'm a real
developmentalists so I'm like ken wilber
yeah ok and now if we were all like you
know Goethe or Walt Whitman we would
change our consciousness to already be
change but so if you look at
developmental stages and see I'm a
psychologist by training and most of my
work is really psychology and Wilbur
really has kind of become a psychologist
and he does a very good job with
disappointing out that what's the world
perspective at each developmental stage
we identify with our with our own family
then we had then as we grow we identify
with our social group or church whatever
community and then as we grow we
identify with her maybe our nation and
then eventually we can identify with our
own species
but you've got to practically be a
Buddhist Saint before you can identify
with all life and that's not really the
end of it you want to identify with the
whole cosmos so we don't have the time
or the means or the likelihood
this is a realistic side of it for me of
promoting and facilitating that kind of
growth in large numbers of people would
like to but it's just not realistic what
is realistic is finding at each level
what is needed to facilitate things at
all levels or at higher levels that is
Kim rubbers written about this quite a
bit he calls it the
[Music]
scale wizard or the growth was if you
want to talk to people
for example Republicans in the US you've
got to talk to them about what they're
interested in yeah their own security
the security of their children the
future of their children I think most of
them are trying to be interested in that
you've got to find leverage points that
are different for different
developmental levels and what people
want what they need it's insoluble so
that's I mean it's not general
philosophy that's not and I disagree
with urban I'm not gonna pop the world
exactly I thank you for speaking to that
because that's where I was going and the
I find I mean urban is one of the people
who really have promoted this paradigm
shift story and I I find that there's
deep wisdom in the fact that when
Donella Meadows wrote her paper places
to intervene in a system there was a
there's a first version and a second
version of that paper in the first
version she ends at the level of
paradigm she says that's the highest
leverage point and then she 10 years
later just before she died she wrote
another version of the same paper which
later ended up in her posthumous book
and where she says no there is another
level which is to go beyond paradigm and
do the way I interpret that is exactly
what you're saying is not to make the
mistake which we constantly do in the
history of humanity of over swinging the
pendulum of going from one extreme view
to another opposing extreme view like a
thesis antithesis rather than coming
into a synthesis that that has exactly
that wisdom that you just spoke to that
we will never live on a planet where a
baby is born with a kind of Humboldt
Goethe type consciousness yeah it's part
of evolving and so we need to like what
you just said like the the adage that
spiral dynamics likes to say you have to
speak to people where they're at or not
where you want them to be
how do we communicate about this and
keep the spiral or this developmental
pathway that the will becomes matrix
open enough and healthy enough so at
each developmental stage people can live
out that particular view of the world
without sabotaging the future of life on
earth because what what right now is
that people are stuck in like in in
spiral dynamics color language terms
they're stuck in unhealthy blue or
unhealthy orange or even unhealthy red
and so that they're highly competitive
or they're highly dogmatic or they're
highly competitive in them in a more
sort of intellectual really kind of way
and and how do we get people into a
space where we we heal each of those
levels and make them regenerative so
people can go through that cycle and
keep transcendence include as will the
likes to call it keep the the best of
that perspective be able to drop into
that perspective if life conditions
require so M but to constantly keep the
pathway open to a wider and deeper
understanding of our unity with with
life and the universe answers to
real-world problems but I think you've
outlined the issue very well and we're
facing some very difficult problems
politically and personally it's always
been a characteristic of organisms
especially higher organisms to go for
short-term gains over a long term
punishment or a long term losses
and that's kind of what we're done with
the environment I think we're saying oh
well we got a few years enjoy life and
and not really addressing long-term
problems although ironically it seems
like some of the countries in the world
that are least in the quranic' our most
serious about China for example about
looking at what's gonna be down the road
but I don't really know how to do this I
is Ken points out you have to speak to
people in their own language it's her
own level there's a wonderful in ways it
makes sense to them is that there's a
wonderful paper that and I take it you
know Barrett Brown don't you he wrote a
peaceful and I think it was unconscious
in in cosmos Journal and there was
entitled communicating sustainability
where he used the sort of inspired by
Wilbur inspired by spiral dynamics and
based on on Sean SP and Huggins work in
Michael Zimmerman's work he he teased
apart different perspectives on the
environmental issue I can't remember the
whole thing but he has like the
eco-warrior in the eco strategist and if
you come across it I don't want to send
you on a fishing trip on your computer I
would love to see that I would love to
see or a reference to at least the the
book you've mentioned previously with
paradigms and then it was he said it was
written the essay was written ten years
later and published posthumously yeah
I'm not familiar with this and I would
really like to see it know I glad I
gladly send you send you links to both
of them and great I mean because you've
you've done so much work also with art
and literature and the cultural aspect
of the human expression of where we
basically perceive
the world and then we we try to make
sense of that experience throughout and
culture and and I I often feel like I
had this wonderful moment in 2006 when I
visited David or at Oberlin and
interviewed him about his work and I
asked him what he thought the dimension
of spirituality and the sacred was in
the transition that is now ahead of us
and David gave me a really good answer
where he said a number of things but
among them he said before we can find
meaningful answers and sensible answers
to what we need to do to be sustainable
and how we might go about achieving that
we have to ask ourself a much deeper
question which is what is it about our
very young species that right now is one
of the youngest on the planet like we
haven't even lived 1% of the normal
average lifetime of a species on earth
how what is it about us that could be
used in favor of our species as an
argument of why we should have a chance
of living a few more 10 thousands or
even millions of years from from your
deep study of the human condition and
what makes you hopeful rather than
distraught about our species very well
you know there's something radically
different about human beings compared to
other species or at least almost
radically different I see that Ranga
Tang has recently gained personhood in
the court somewhere I have
double-checked the article but there's
something about the human intelligence
the human mind that's just radically
different what can I say
and we get one of the first signs of
intelligence we see evolutionary is art
appearing in caves for example and
musical instruments such as flutes made
from animal bones and so on so I view
the arts including well the humanities
in general is one of the most valuable
features of human existence and borders
on spiritual it's hard to make a
distinction really because throughout
history a great deal of part has been
spiritual and you can't hardly separate
them same is true with music but why
we're worth more than other organisms I
don't really know that we are I don't
really have an answer for why we should
continue to exist I wasn't at all trying
to apply that in any way we are more
workers than others but but what I and I
think well you're you did answer it
because there are expressions that we
like in in in the answer to that
question David also said that we we are
meaning seeking creatures for and he
actually started at exactly the same
place where you just started from that
first time will you spit some paint
against right on a cave wall to have
that imprint that's a sign of a species
that is asking Who am I and where do I
come from where am I going and and that
it's it's this process of of meaning
creation that where I also feel like
maybe we can create a convincing enough
narrative of our past our significance
and our potential of serving life that
could be expressed in slightly different
language with slightly different sort of
hot buttons and cold buttons so to speak
yeah speak to the different levels of
consciousness that you UN can mapped out
that the developmental power but that
have a common theme that that ink
actually includes in the narrative that
journey of deeper deepening of
perspective broadening as part of being
connected um I'm thinking out loud here
well you've thought about this more
deeply than I have that's pretty clear
I'm a big fan of young captures view of
well he didn't call it evolution of
consciousness because he didn't want to
get tangled up with some of the
evolutionary arguments that have and do
go on but he certainly looked at
evolution as a developmental process and
I mean consciousness over time he has
these various social psychological
stages and he talks about integral
consciousness
and I think he talks about it in a way
that is more satisfying to me personally
if I wanted to say I don't want to
criticize chin Wilbur but I will say
that chin is a very cognitive guy I
think of him as very Apollonian he's the
brilliance of the mind and and captures
notion of integral and he said here's
what he said it to be integral to live
all structures at all times now Ken
would disagree with that because he's
you want to go up levels and if you go
out four levels the lower levels come
under control of the higher level
it's a whole different kind of concept
is much more PJ and I guess but what
what gebser was interested in was having
all levels active at any moment and I
mean you think what this means magical
is about poetry about music especially
about music mythic is about imagination
mental is of course oh we all know what
mental is we've got too much of it so
the point being that a rich life
somebody asked me once how do you
educate a person or train them to tip
for internal consciousness and I said
senator liberal arts college let them
learn music of literature and philosophy
and use their mind and use their
emotions so you know when I look around
my office I have several translations of
the Odyssey and the Iliad for example
and mythic stories and so on and these
enrich life I'm not a very religious
person but religion is about myth and a
pound away so these are the things that
give life meaning come on
to me that that gets a perspective of
integral is so much healthier then that
make it way whether Kenan is doing this
actively or passively I don't think he's
meaning to do it actively somehow the
reading of a lot of people in the
integral or the spiral dynamics
community I mean I used to teach on
courses the principles of spiral
dynamics and it didn't matter how many
times I said it's not about types of
people it's about types in people it's
um it's a delivery thing and everybody
at the end of the class people will go
oh you're so blue or you're so orange
and however say their service to their
point of view and people would get
competitive and it's the same if you
look in the console
see world like everybody said like this
there's a whole bunch of people out
there who set up consultancies to help
companies to become teal organizations
or and I that just sets up a false
competitiveness of in a one-upmanship of
who I'm so much better because I can see
the world from a turquoise perspective
instead of saying we need the whole
healthy spectrum well I agree and it's
difficult because each of us has had our
own place sees the world from our own
perspective in some sense so it involves
a lot of humility and recognizing that
other people have valid points of view
and in order to get anywhere and move
forward in any practical political real
world sense we have to get inside of
those and help those people actualize
the best parts of those perspectives
they have so for example what
perspective isn't where you find
traditional religions Mormonism for
example well there's no point in arguing
with them about it or trying to you know
move them on but you've got a lot of
time on your hands and they're willing
to listen but what can you do to
facilitate their worldview in a way that
is compatible with others and will help
in the big a bigger picture now I'm
going to tell you you don't know you've
thought about these things much more
than me understand surely a psychologist
and a philosopher I just would love to
like what what I said well for me is so
nice to be able to to just compare and
contrast like because a lot of this view
that that I've developed is also
influenced by one of my mentors um Brian
Goodwin who was a bio Brown who's
wonderful and and Brian was the first
like from a complexity perspective
to zero it doesn't really make sense to
explain life and consciousness ex nihilo
and it makes so much money evades the
entire complexity and when like at the
baguette there the quote that I read at
the beginning you say conscious is not
an epidermal on of the brain Brian also
completely pointed this out that and
Gregory Bateson that mind and
consciousness is not inside this skull
coming out of just brain activity and
what why do you say that and like I
agree but but um when where do you see
the seat of consciousness then Oh what
now that's a whole different question I
think probably looking for the seat of
consciousness and further wrong-minded
question yeah maybe that was bad no why
do you say that um like how do we get
away from the view that
consciousness is an epitome an
epiphenomenon of brain activity and how
can we explain it yeah well you're right
is the heart of one of the deepest
enigmas that we know of relationship of
the mind of the brain and it's full of
paradoxes as I said I tend to be
something of a paying psychist which
means that I think consciousness is why
the distributed in the cosmos and really
a part of it and certainly part of
higher organisms but with the brain it's
very I mean I'm teaching a course on
consciousness right now and here on the
one hand we know that certain kinds of
brain disorders profoundly affect
consciousness in fact I we had a whole
seminar at one of the Tucson meetings a
few years ago about the locked-in
syndrome and this is what a person's had
serious a serious stroke in their
conscious and a wage and they can't
control anything of their body except
usually their eye movements you know
there's a movie and a book called the
butterfly in the diving belt
written by a person who was actually in
the locked-in syndrome but was able to
communicate by looking at letters one
after another really big painting the
book okay so I have students that would
like to think consciousness is free of
the brain everybody had to put up with
that sort of thing on the other hand we
do know that people have out of the body
experiences they seem to be quite valid
or these have been studied sometimes in
dreams sometimes in near-death
experiences clearly people have
experiences out of the body but they
seem to be out of the body and they seem
to locate themselves out of the body I
should talk a lot about that that's kind
of thing that interests me but the fact
that it's a consciousness can in some
sense be out of the body and
in some very real sense is non-local
it's a lot of people are liking to call
it nowadays so how is it possible why is
it so connected to the brain and so
independent of the brain at the same
time I don't know it's a mystery this is
again an area of science that some
people find hard to venture into but
Dena Robbins work on remote viewing for
example this just seems to have been in
Norfolk documented cases of people being
able to remote view which would would
kind of speak to the non-local potential
yeah yeah but you probably have seen it
here too old real magic and hadn't seen
it now oh it's a great little book I
actually wrote to him about it because I
wrote a book
years and years ago on synchronicity and
he has a whole section of synchronicity
synchronistic events in that book which
he attributes to magic real magic and I
don't disagree with him but we you know
we approach it from two different
directions and we both seem to be coming
to the same conclusions for example
during the founding of Finn horn there
were you know what's his name
Peter yeah I mean he created no place
out of either magic or seeker in this
year ever you want to call it it was
just an amazing story I should I heard
him talk about it you probably met him
but where am I was this clearly yeah
remote viewing is very real when it
works and there's just so many
experiences people have out of the body
experiences during surgery where they
can tell you what the room looks like
from up at the ceiling or even maybe
they went down the hall and say what's
going on down there and another whole
area that that I know that some of your
colleagues at CIS have been
investigating is and for me this is also
an M
a deeper question of inquiry is like I
in my past I've done some experimenting
with psychoactive substances that expand
your perception in a circle so we have a
new program in a research program I keep
keep wondering whether one of the
reasons why we couldn't disconnected so
profoundly from life as the wider
community that actually makes it
possible for us to live our life or deep
into being as technicon called it with
the more than human world and to my mind
maybe our taboo on these type of sacred
plants and the use of these sacred
plants has closed the door of our
breadth of the awareness that that our
species through its evolution has just
always been engaged with like I mean
there's even people who who suggest that
possibly that's what enabled to jump
from a primate brain that is pretty
complex and has pretty complex things to
a homo sapiens or mahabali's brain that
that clearly is more complex than that
and and also in terms of behavioral
pattern and spectrum that there may be
the use of these plants has actually
been a key element in our evolution they
really we're seeing especially here in
California but resurgence of serious
interest in psychotropic there were now
they're calling them in thien's
where we still cycle psychedelic drugs
or agents
these have clearly been a feature of
human experience any for as long as
there have been humans one of the
popular ones right now I shouldn't use
the word popular but you know it's uh oh
what's it called now I'm speaking too
quick ayahuasca hmm yeah don't try this
at home very powerful drug but I have
students now psychedelic experiences and
haven't had them since the 60s so
research is going on it's now becoming
at least accepted that these drugs might
be helpful in medical ways but whether
they help earth the human mind or not I
don't know I certainly wouldn't argue
against it I think if you go back far
enough people are yeah we will ever find
a clear answer to that but but I think
it is a valid question to explore
because I mean it does from my
experiences particularly with with
psilocybin um it it really brings you
more interior intuitive connected animal
body and your whole way of perceiving oh
so sorry we'll do a mescaline desert to
Iceland does to it makes you very
embodied in the way probably horny it's
another way of the wider yeah yeah I
just I just sensed that that maybe we've
we've possibly through the Catholic
Church I don't know when when that taboo
came in so strongly but of the use of
these substances is partially the giving
over the spirit
to a priest rather than to actively in
community I have experiences and deeper
spiritual connection to a wider hole
through ceremony with I mean that
there's a big difference I find between
the ceremonial use of these substances
and the kind of recreational use of
these substances and I think if the
recreational use can be very dangerous
and in kind of pleasure-seeking and and
not necessarily healthy and and but the
the using the mass sacrament as a way of
what we call the recreational use is
often valuable opening up new channels
of understanding in reality I've met and
you should you have to ensure people who
have served awakened to a larger
universe through LSD or some other agent
and then pursue a life of searching and
you know a broader life of interest and
searching and looking into oneself
because of that category I don't know
what which came first the chicken or the
egg but but yeah well of course that was
the problem in the sixties people would
take these drugs and then they wouldn't
be Republicans anymore so yes so
strongly crack down on them and but by
the way we just we just lost a month or
two ago friend of mine that live Bernier
made rough mr. mm-hmm probably there was
no man alive who knew as much about
alternate alternative states of
consciousness and psychoactive agencies
my troth Nets mister who continued to
write about these things throughout his
whole life and as long as we're talking
about him I'm talking about it one of
his last books was felled the ecology of
consciousness
which is the titles a little tricky
because it suggests that it's involved
in his green consciousness' work which
is a little different but the ecology of
consciousness it's just a huge book of
every topic you can think of collecting
his experience totally fascinating I've
read a lot of myths in the 20 years ago
when it was a true Mahakali I read
anything since to that I'll pick up on
that there's a there's a couple of more
things that I wanted to get your
perspective on because so like this
there's this big question what is life
what is consciousness and but there's
also one that I think might be a little
bit downriver from it which is what is
time like the way we perceive so much of
how we perceive time and how we locate
ourselves with relationship to the past
the present and the future maybe even
the sense that we currently have of that
linear era of time but it says the past
is in behind us and the future is in
front of us is to my mind the emergent
property that like that it's it's an
experience that emerges out of how we
explain our participatory agency in the
world so so basically if we don't like
there seems to be an illusion of time
the it makes for me perfect sense that
like JG Bennett had this very complex
notion of time using all these Greek
terms like hypothesis and so on where he
opened up the possibility that the past
and the future are Co present in the one
place that we can ever only be which is
the experiential moment of the of now M
what's your take on time and and it's
it's totally baffling I've been
fascinated by time myself for many years
recently I've realized how tightly it's
connected to the questioner pretty well
for example William James talked about
this quite a bit he you know if you
well--there's it was for the block
universe you're probably familiar with
this notion James talked about well the
block universe is just says that theater
is some big multi-dimensional block I
think you would find at nine Stein and
if any system that says you can move
forwards and backwards in it suggests
that it somehow is fixed it's you know
so the block universe if you believe in
time travel you believe in a block
universe because it's still there
somewhere and you can go backwards and
forwards and of course if you stick to
very traditional physics you can run the
equations backwards and forwards it's a
very Newtonian view so that's the block
universe and probably most views of
evolution and a time come somehow out of
the block universe view a but you can't
have free will anything like that I
don't think it suggests everything is
already predetermined forwards and
backwards so where's the free will the
other view one I'm a big proponent of
but doesn't allow time travel so it's
too bad for some of the stories is the
process view in that time is really
defined by the ongoing process of the
cosmos and forward process you can't go
backwards in fact it's very closely
related to complexity theory and chaos
that when you drop a cube of sugar in a
cup of hot coffee
dissolves in the molecule still in every
direction well that's a process process
for you the way time works in fact you
can't run it back we can't put it back
together again although maybe Newton
said but you and I can't so I'm training
remember there's a physicist who has
written about this a lot and continues
to write very popular I could the amount
sending time thing is Solomon for some
maaske reason I'm driving distillation
what's that
well David Bohm had a very interesting
angle on untighten and the that saw time
much more and yeah as a process and well
he was a big process thinker yeah but it
was really who wasn't to develop the
view of time really in a fundamental way
I should have made notes be there in
trouble remembering he doesn't know
about winning physicist that talks about
creativity if you want to talk about
creativity you can't do the block
universe either so his name will
probably come to me because it's so
associated with time consciousness and
creativity so that's I have a process
view time but it's it's a big mystery
yeah but now that you brought up the
topic I'm reading a book called time
loops mm-hmm have you ever heard of this
book
no conducts time loops and it's by eric
Wargo w arg oh very far go and I mention
this because if you try to find time
loops at Amazon or something you'll see
eight or ten books most in science
fiction Oh Argo is a recent PhD from the
University of Georgia and seen an
anthropologist and he has done an
amazingly scholarly job of looking at
possibility that people experience the
future the near future in very concrete
ways and dreams and visions and so on
and here's the catch these future
visions feed back to what we do today
mm-hmm and I mean he makes it
fascinating case for this sort of thing
for example I won't go into detail be
thought about this right now or but the
famous are you sure maybe with a very
famous Carl Jung synchronicity case of
the scarab beetle Chuck yeah when you
yeah well there you know so so this lady
is good and she's a client she's gonna
go see her therapist Carl Jung who's
famous for his weird and wonderful
mystical ideas about occultism and
everything else and she how does this
work she essentially creates the event
where she talks about the Scarabaeus
people and and and and he waves his hand
and catches one in his hand and the
bailiff oh yeah
but the point is that she had dreams
about this sort of thing ahead of time
and did she create an event from the
dream I'd have you better look through
it interesting because so many of the
indigenous wisdom holders have a deep
deep attention to dreaming that again
our culture doesn't but if original
culture but but anywhere in the world
and indigenous cultures pay a lot of
attention to dreams and and I think I've
had a number of experiences in my life
where I would see a place seemingly for
the first time and then after having
seen it I would have this and I still
can't really put my hand in the fire for
it what I would call either real or
false there's a mood of saying wow the
place we saw today I dreamt about years
ago in that dream where I woke up
thinking how much detail was in this
dream why did I in this dream go into
such detail about a particular place and
then suddenly three years later I find
myself in in exactly enjoy this book yes
even it gets even more complex because
of the dream you had about this thing
the future may affect the way you
respond to it when you get there so
there's this sort of feedback that's
very weird and when I first heard it I
couldn't take it seriously at all but
now that I've been reading it it does a
wonderful job you know I can't really
recall the detailed stories right now I
wish I could but he really realized
Freud and a lot of the stuff about the
unconscious and shows that it could be
in fact a product that this sort of
weird reality and was people see things
in the future and innocence and create
them and so this was real
and I don't know I'm not doing a very
good job of describing it but his
treatment of Jung and Freud the
unconscious and a lot of the symbolic
material in relation to this strange
business about time and it also has a
fascinating chapter about the science
fiction writer what's his name
a philip k dick mm-hmm you know
two-thirds of the science fiction movies
come straight out of philip k dick he
lived near me in California and he had
precognitive dreams all the time he
based his story about a lot of them and
it's just very weird and one interesting
stuff so anyway finally look into like
maybe I'll even call him up and have a
conversation with him at some point he
will talk to his young PhD by the way he
talked at Esalen about a year ago and
people were very impressed by the the
last question I would love your
perspective on is another thing that
I've got is wonderful it's it's number
somehow related to the notion of time
like this idea of the co-presence of the
past and the future in the now I
recently learned from a Maori elder um
that the maari's have a concept of time
which is called wha and that there is
basically that that the potential of
manifesting is informed by the past but
it the reap a turning which then
manifests as a future is happening in
the now and in a related understanding
to that is that in in the Western world
we have this bizarre false dualism
between so many things like humanity and
nature self and world mind and matter
and one of the the other really bad
falls dualism that sabotages us is this
false dualism between theory and
practice that that seems to suggest that
our conversation right now
has absolutely zero agency in the
universe until we form an action plan
and then go out and implement whatever
we've decided the actions should be and
the outcome should be but if everything
is non locally connected and there's a
much more dynamic relationship between
consciousness and matter and
consciousness is possibly primary in
matter secondary then any kind of
interaction and sense making in the
consciousness space in us having a
conversation actually does have physical
agency across the universe and does that
make any sense to you whatsoever I know
well I've always been prone to be a soft
knee for weird wonderful ideas and this
is London one of them but I you know
recently I've seen more and more and
heard more and more that really makes me
wonder about these things this book by
that I just mentioned about time time
lives really makes you wonder about the
nature of time and Dean Radin spot real
magic he's working on another one I have
his email address he might be interest
in hearing from you his discussion of
remote viewing and some other but he's a
real scientist now he's in the lab no
bullshit for him but yes so he's finding
an interesting guy can get his attention
he's not an academic and he's kind of
reclusive but he's very rigorous in his
sinking but I did finally remember the
guy was trying to tell you the physicist
ilya prigogine of course we've heard of
it yeah what yeah and he
he his concept of time is based on
process in which you know it's like the
dissolving of the sugar cube things
scattered disorder increases in some way
he's not one of the people that argued
that we're all running downhill it's
just that this process of change that's
inherent and everything in the universe
is the fundamental definition of time
it's a definition of time that's not
Newtonian you can't run it backwards and
it gives birth to all manner creativity
so I don't have a listeners books in
front of me now but you'll see that he
and others that have worked with him
let's say Illiad pretty much with a B
books order out of chaos that's one of
his book I'm familiar with this way yeah
well there you know he used to be a lot
of the conferences I would come to were
number them with the urban Lazlo so I've
heard him speak a number of times and
he's very impressive you know this is
not his main thing he's got something
else he's very interested in well he's
gone now but yeah this alternative you
know time and there's a physicist been
writing very nice stuff about it if you
want me to follow up I'll try to
remember that I just can't think of his
name right now if you do remember and I
want to take another deep dive into
people's perspective on time because
it's something that as early as when I
did my master's in holistic science at
Omaha College in 2001 2002 I should have
concluded it our like in the you know
the over quoted statement of Einstein
that we can't solve the problems that
we've created in the thinking that
created them in the first place and we
need first need to change the way we
think about things I I sense that our
spective on time is crucial to making a
jump to a different way of reaper
sieving our role in in this in this
process well here here's a book by him
I'm looking at my kindle Lee Smolin as
him oli in amazing joy he's a real fish
that mean he's a real theoretical
citizen since highly regarded from the
crisis in physics to the future the
universe Lee Smolin I remember with
Linda's presents published recently and
it's titled time reborn okay time to
excellent and from the New York Times
Book Review at once entertaining thought
for publishing fabulously ambitious and
fabulously especially these books are
very readable
please small and young oh my friend
Brian slim do you know Sabra
I mean chance is a big fan of Lee Smolin
as well Brian like some that's an even
stronger
in terms of people following up with
your work
what's the if if somebody hasn't read
any of your books yet what would you
recommend is the best place to start
well the easiest book to read is and
probably a good place to start would be
consciousness explained better that's a
small book I really wrote at Ken
Wilbur's request to write a readable
popular book about his his theory of
consciousness system you know
consciousness he complimented me by
feeling that I could write a better book
than he could in terms of readability
he's a wonderful writer they say he read
one or two thousand wasp books out loud
before he started reading writing
himself to get some style my book the
radiance of being is about twenty years
old but it's there's not much in there
that's really out of date and it goes
into my view of consciousness see we
don't have time to talk about this but
everything I ever did had to do a system
Siri hmm and I used system theory to
develop a view of consciousness and
states of consciousness and so on and
it's pretty system mathematically laid
out in that book I've written a number
of articles most of them co-authored
with Stanley Crippler that represented
the displaying this view and I could
send you one of those and you'll do fine
- but terms of readability probably
consciousness explained better yeah no I
think I read both of those and I think
consciousness explained better is
definitely the the entry level and then
if people want to go deeper and
understand some of the concepts deeper
then the radiance of being is kind of
the Graduate version now that's the
Graduate tips but one thing about the
much more recent consciousness explained
better is it really goes into some
detail I don't say technical staff
that's just an idea but some detail
about the idea of perspective because
the four quadrants when you get really
down into them our perspectives they're
not objects they're not not categories
in the world their perspectives and I
really work to try to communicate that
notion in that book I feel like I did a
passable job of it well you want won
lots of awards for best science writing
and for that book so it is really really
well-written and can you can you say say
a couple of things more way you teach
because you currently teach an online
course through CIS and you people well
California scenario studies there's a
department be called
PCC
philosophy cosmology and consciousness
where Brian swim who else and makan
[Music]
Shawn Kenny yeah Shawn Kelly there are
some others but those are the two
closest to the kinds of things were
talking about today and habit lady who's
a new anthropologist there and she's
interested in ecology for sure but Brian
and Sean I teach in a program called
transformative studies which is much
more related to the social sciences and
I in fact I'm the only one in the
program that's sort of a philosophical
psychologist but it's very open-ended
that students I have a number students
studying different aspects of
consciousness for their dissertations
and I offered two courses on
consciousness the introductory course
and one on the brain and then I teach
them election just summer I'll teach an
elective on consciousness in history of
art which I essentially lineup the
historical kept Syrian stage and so it's
works of art and we talk about them try
to have some fun with them I mean oh I
remember you giving a presentation on
that and when you came and taught a
couple of courses a sprint on college
and gave the talk it's ride I love that
presentation it's a lot of fun because I
haven't taught it for several years you
should you should video like is there
has anybody ever did you'd you giving
that presentation with that wonderful
slideshow um well we've talked about my
son comic book artist and we've talked
about making a comic book of the history
of art hmm and he's up for it if we can
just find some time for him to work on
it and one of my colleagues
transdisciplinary scholar Alfonso
Montori has encouraged me to write a
book so what
need is a year to write a book and not
to teach I guess there's so many things
that one can do that actually there may
be you may have some interests as you
said there's a there's a student from
PCC from that program he's now graduated
who's become a good friend of mine
Linda cherry and she has she's a
filmmaker she's made a wonderful film on
human potential kinds of a lot of
incident with trans tech trans
technology it was this whole area now
there's even brain stimulation do EEG
learning and training so she's written a
dissertation that looks at ways to human
potential can be optimized and it
includes everything from traditional
meditation to psychedelic agents that
can be used to expand human mind the all
kinds of electronics and stuff now you
open up another box and I was sorry
that's okay no I was just about to wrap
up but but that is now too too big of a
question to leave hanging on em which is
because I actually had it somewhere in
my notes I wanted to ask you about this
as well which is I'm really concerned by
the transhumanist agenda and the
transhumanist story this whole kind of I
know that in the Bay Area it's almost
impossible to not believe in with we're
trapped in a situation of runaway tech
where technology is evolving so quickly
and we will not be able to put the genie
back into the box or close Pandora's box
and all we can do is to just to serve
dance along with it but I I think that's
a little bit of a fatalistic view I
think part of if we if we are going to
make it as a species we need to develop
a more mature relationship with
technology which
to my mind is about choosing what
technologies to use and what not to use
and understand that technology should be
serving us and we shouldn't be serving
technology and increasingly it's the
other way around so I'm not a
transhumanist we're looking at things
that have shown benefits Alzheimer's
patients help people overcome depression
and whatever those in Moore's a better
self-control better regulation of pain I
don't I'm not one of those people that
thinks we can upload our brain computer
or any that actually the person that
designs the brain you want to try with
that for what's-her-name the robot that
now is a person in Saudi Arabia Sophia
if you ever see if you ever listened it
Sophia thought and she's an Android
mm-hmm I have to do is look on youtubes
of for Sophia and interview with Sophia
she's actually been as I said given a
citizenship I think maybe she thought
she she's designed to look like Audrey
Hepburn good-looking robot yeah and
their friend of Mines the guy who
designed the designer computer and my
wife says is very scary yeah I don't
have an opinion either way but I but
been Gert so the guy that did this old
friend of mine chaos theory friend he
was at one of the tucson conference and
somebody said Jesus this is really scary
what are we gonna do when Easter know
these things these quote-unquote people
whose robots take over and Ben said well
I'd rather turn my politics over to a
well programmed robots in the
Ben's got this little thing hanging
around his neck the biggest in the car
accident got off his head and freeze it
right away he can't afford to freeze the
old body
so but no I told me we had this long
discussion I said no no I plan to come
back it's a baby I'm not doing this
incarnations you know it would be no I
think that's it's it's a deeply it's
kind of the utmost perversion of the
mechanistic consciousness and the kind
of Hans Moravec and records what while
version of transhumanism that we will
download our very and put it into a
robot and then we will live forever and
it's both on the brain okay so this it
this has been really wonderful we talk
for longer and then I thought we would
but and I really learned a lot and thank
you so much for this time I'm just gonna
stop the recording and then we can say
goodbye and so thanks so much